Penmaen Press Records
© 2002 University of Connecticut
Penmaen Press Records.
1967-1999.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
McCurdy, Michael.
6 linear feet.
The Penmaen Press was an imprint created by its proprietor, Michael McCurdy, with the goal of producing high quality hand-printed books. McCurdy designed and supervised the layout of each Penmaen production, and frequently supplied his own woodcut engravings as illustrations.
MSS19990025
History
Michael McCurdy earned his B.F.A. and M.F.A. degrees from the graphic arts department of the School of the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston, though his interest in hand-printing stems back to a toy press that he received as a present at the age of twelve. McCurdy worked as a freelance illustrator and engraver for a number of years, but also retained an interest in printing his own books. His first production, Genesis, was published under the imprint of the Hillside Press, but this name had to be changed after McCurdy discovered another printer using the same name on the other side of Beacon Hill in Boston. The first Penmaen Press publication was Quaker Queries in 1969. The Penmaen name comes from a town in Wales; McCurdy came upon the name in Gerard Manley Hopkins' poem "Penmaen Pool."
The Penmaen Press became a full-time operation for McCurdy in 1975. Over the next ten years the press developed a diverse catalogue of publications, including original works of poetry by writers such as Leo Connellan and Richard Eberhart as well as short stories by William Saroyan and Lynne Sharon Schwartz. The Penmaen Press also produced broadsides of poems by Lawrence Ferlinghetti and Allen Ginsberg. Many Penmaen works feature engravings by Michael McCurdy, though other engravers (such as Lynd Ward) have also been featured.
In 1984, Michael McCurdy and Robert Hauser formed a partnership to produce Face to Face: Twelve Contemporary American Artists Interpret Themselves in a Limited Edition of Original Wood Engravings. Engravers who submitted self-portraits for this project include McCurdy, Barry Moser, Fritz Eichenberg, John DePol, and others.
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of correspondence and other materials relating to projects undertaken by McCurdy under the Penmaen imprint. Project folders typically include correspondence, manuscript drafts, galley proofs, and publicity materials relating to the work (sometimes including reviews). The published versions of most of these works are available through the Dodd Center (the call numbers are listed in a note at the end of this finding aid). The materials making up the Face to Face project are comprehensive, detailing preliminary visions for the project, working correspondence with each of the contributors, and specific records dealing with the binding and production of the finished work. The collection also includes broadsides signed by Lawrence Ferlinghetti and Allen Ginsberg.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in a single series, with most materials placed in folders according to the title of the related project. Some oversized publicity materials as well as the Ferlinghetti broadside are shelved in a separate map case folder.
Related Material
Archives and Special Collections has a substantial collection of rare publications relating to twentieth-century American poetry, as well as the records of other literary presses. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk. See also Penmaen/Busyhaus Collection.
Separated Material
Seven issues of Coda: The Poets and Writers Newsletter (LMC)
Accounting. By Lynne Sharon Schwartz. C5465, WPS 3488, WPS 3489
Banquet: Five Short Stories. Edited by Michael McCurdy. C3433
Charlie in the House of Rue. By Robert Coover. C5456, C5457
Crossing America. By Leo Connellan. C4502
The First Ten: A Penmaen Bibliography. Edited by Michael Peich. C3733
Gerard Manley Hopkins Meets Walt Whitman in Heaven and Other Poems. By Phillip Dacey. C5475
King Harald and the Icelanders. C679, C5462
Light of Paradise. By William Ferguson. C278
Listening Deep: Poems. By William Stafford. WPS 3487
A Love for Four Voices. By Anthony Hecht. C5476, WPS 3492
Memory of Snow. By Sándor Csoóri. C5471, C5472, C5473
Poem Upon the Lisbon Disaster. By Voltaire. C3288
Poems to Poets. By Richard Eberhart. B3016
Rosebud: Poems. By Gerard Malanga. C3019
Song of Life. By Sushil Gupta. WPS 3491
These Rooms. By Suzanne Berger. C5474
To Eberhart from Ginsberg: A Letter About Howl, 1956. By Allen Ginsberg. C3013, C3014
Two Poems. By Denise Levertov. WPS 2008
The Woe Shirt: Caribbean Folk Tales. By Paulé Bartón. C5459
World Alone (Mundo a Solas). By Vicente Aleixandre. C5859
Bibliography
The First Ten: A Penmaen Bibliography, Compiled and Edited by Michael Peich. Lincoln, Massachusetts: The Penmaen Press, 1978.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
McCurdy, Michael.
Organizations:
Penmaen Press.
Subjects:
Publishers and publishing--Massachusetts--Lincoln.; Wood engravers--Massachusetts--Lincoln.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Financial Records.; Press releases.; Broadsides.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Manuscripts.; Galley proofs.; Books.; Engravings.; Sketches.
Occupations:
Publisher.; Engraver.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Materials transferred to the Dodd Center directly by Michael McCurdy.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Penmaen Press Projects, 1967-1999
  - Hillside Press Prospectus (limited edition), 1967 (Box 1:1)
  - Penmaen Press publicity brochures and prospectuses, 1975-1983 (Box 1:2)
  - Minor Projects - single poem pamphlets, 1968-1983 (Box 1:3)
  - Press ephemera and publicity items, 1975-1983 (Box 1:4)
  - Cambria Press and Design Studio projects, ca. 1975-1983 (Box 1:5)
  - Personal Ephemera - greeting cards and invitations, 1969-1999 (Box 1:6)
  - Ephemera not related to Penmaen or McCurdy, 1963-1982 (Box 1:7)
  - Correspondence and MS submission letters, 1975-1986 (Box 1:8)
  - Michael Peich
    - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 1:9)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 1:10)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 1:11)
  - Fritz Eichenberg
    - Correspondence, engravings, 1974-1990 (Box 1:12)
    - Publications, clippings, 1954-1990 (Box 1:13)
  - Joseph Blumenthal
    - Correspondence, booklet, clipping, 1985-1990 (Box 1:14)
  - Leo Wyatt
    - Correspondence, bookplates, 1973-1980 (Box 1:15)
  - Quaker Queries
    - Correspondence, design notes, partial proof, review, 1969 (Box 1:16)
  - Light of Paradise
    - Correspondence, typed MS, partial dummy, 1973 (Box 1:17)
  - Celebrations After the Death of John Brennan
    - Correspondence, MS, design notes, dummy, 1974 (Box 1:18)
  - Dove at the Windows
    - Correspondence, photocopies, design notes, 1974 (Box 1:19)
  - Poems to Poets
    - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1:20)
    - Typed MS, dummy, proofs, reference copies, 1975 (Box 1:21)
  - Rosebud
    - Typed MS, 1975 (Box 1:22)
  - Crossing America
    - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1:23-24)
    - Typed MS, dummy, proofs, 1976 (Box 1:25)
    - Reviews, 1976 (Box 1:26)
  - Poem Upon the Lisbon Disaster
    - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1:27)
    - Typed MS, proofs, notes, 1977 (Box 1:28)
  - An Act or Two of Foolish Kindness
    - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2:29)
    - Typed MSS by Saroyan, 1977 (Box 2:30)
  - Banquet
    - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 2:31)
    - Art, proofs, reviews, 1978 (Box 2:32)
    - Typed MSS of stories, 1978 (Box 2:33)
  - The First Ten: A Penmaen Bibliography
    - Correspondence, typed MS, 1978 (Box 2:34)
    - Dummy, galleys, art, proofs, 1978 (Box 2:35)
  - King Harald and the Icelanders
    - Correspondence, typed MS, 1979 (Box 2:36)
    - Galleys, proofs, design materials, 1979 (Box 2:37)
  - Clear Sky, Pure Light
    - Correspondence, brochures, reviews, 1979 (Box 2:38)
    - Galleys, 1979 (Box 2:39)
  - The Love Nut
    - Correspondence, MS, corrected proof, art sketch, 1979 (Box 2:40)
  - These Rooms
    - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2:41)
    - Typed MS, proofs, 1979 (Box 2:42)
    - Proofs, notes, reviews, 1979 (Box 2:43)
  - Charlie in the House of Rue
    - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2:44)
    - Galleys, proofs, 1980 (Box 2:45)
    - Typed MS, cover design, reviews, publicity, 1980 (Box 2:46)
  - Passion
    - Correspondence, MS, 1980 (Box 2:47)
    - Proofs, galleys, art proofs, notes, 1980 (Box 2:48)
  - The Woe Shirt
    - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2:49)
    - Typed MS, jacket design, galleys, reviews, 1980 (Box 2:50)
  - Eleonora
    - Correspondence, typed MS, galleys, 1981 (Box 2:51)
  - Elizabeth
    - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 3:52)
    - Typed MS, 1981 (Box 3:53)
    - Galleys, 1981 (Box 3:54)
    - Proofs, reviews, 1981 (Box 3:55)
  - Gerard Manley Hopkins Meets Walt Whitman in Heaven and Other Poems
    - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 3:56)
    - Typed MS, 1982 (Box 3:57)
    - Galleys, 1982 (Box 3:58)
    - Proofs, photos, reviews, publicity materials, 1982 (Box 3:59)
  - World Alone
    - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 3:60)
    - Typed MS, photocopies, galleys, 1982 (Box 3:61)
    - Proofs, publicity, reviews, 1982 (Box 3:62)
  - Memory of Snow
    - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 3:63)
    - Typed MS, 1983 (Box 3:64)
    - Cover design, galleys, reviews, photos, 1983 (Box 3:65)
  - The Accounting
    - Correspondence, typed MS, 1983 (Box 3:66)
  - Chapbook series - correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 3:67)
  - A Love for Four Voices
    - Correspondence, galleys, partial proof, 1983 (Box 3:68)
  - Listening Deep
    - Correspondence, MS, galleys, 1984 (Box 3:69)
  - Face to Face
    - Robert Hauser correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 3:70)
    - Robert Hauser correspondence, 1984 (Box 3:71)
    - Robert Kent correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 3:72)
    - Preliminary correspondence with Ellenport, Aaronson and Fuster, Berkshire Bank, 1983-1984 (Box 3:73)
    - Correspondence with binder and typesetter, 1984-1985 (Box 3:74)
    - Jeffery Dwyer correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 3:75)
    - 'Special' correspondence, inquiries, 1985 (Box 4:76)
    - Dealer Contracts, Correspondence, 1983-1987 (Box 4:77)
    - Promotional Materials - Correspondence, Notices, Ads, 1984-1985 (Box 4:78)
    - Promotional Materials - Correspondence, Notices, Ads, 1985-1986 (Box 4:79)
    - Publicity and Sales Mailings, 1984 (Box 4:80)
    - Cost Sheets, foreword and colophon MS, notes, ca. 1984-1985 (Box 4:81)
    - Notices to all artists, 1984-1987 (Box 4:82)
    - Lettering and title designs, 1984 (Box 4:83)
    - Design notes for prospectus, 2 copies of prospectus, 1984-1985 (Box 4:84)
    - Notes and materials, ca. 1984 (Box 4:85)
    - Prospectus for trade book, ca. 1985 (Box 4:86)
    - Reference publications, 1983-1984 (Box 4:87)
    - Contract materials, 1984-1989 (Box 4:88)
    - Copyright paperwork, 1985-1986 (Box 4:89)
    - Insurance and tax correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 4:90)
    - Artist biography proofs, ca. 1984 (Box 4:91)
    - Leonard Baskin materials, 1977-1984 (Box 4:92)
    - Fred Becker correspondence, 1984 (Box 4:93)
    - Bernard Brussel-Smith correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 4:94)
    - Jack Coughlin correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 4:95)
    - John DePol correspondence and engravings, 1983-1985 (Box 4:96)
    - Fritz Eichenberg correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 4:97)
    - Raymond Gloeckler correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 4:98)
    - James Grashow correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 4:99)
    - Judith Jaidinger correspondence, 1983-1990 (Box 4:100)
    - Misch Kohn correspondence, 1984 (Box 4:101)
    - Clare Leighton correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 4:102)
    - Stefan Martin correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 4:103)
    - Michael McCurdy notes and illustrations, 1984 (Box 4:104)
    - Barry Moser and Harold McGrath correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 4:105)
    - Gillian Tyler correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 4:106)
    - Lynd Ward correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 4:107)
    - Herbert Waters correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 4:108)
  - Press Ephemera (oversize sales fliers) and broadside, "The Poets Observe the Absence of God from the St. Louis Zoo.", 1969-1985 (Box OS:109)
  - Mounted Broadside of "The Love Nut" by Lawrence Ferlinghetti, signed by Ferlinghetti and Michael McCurdy, 1979 (Box OS:110)
  - Allen Ginsberg broadside, "Moloch," signed by Ginsberg and Lynd Ward, 1978 (Box OS:111)
  - Oversize Proof Sheet for "Moloch" with numerous comments and corrections by Ginsberg, ca. 1978 (Box OS:112)